<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<Search><pages Count="18"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[The Easterly






                                                                                  ISSUE 2 | OCTOBER 2020


   Cine Appétit

















































































    Follow us on:                                                         www.theeasterly.online]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[ISSUE  2 | OCTOBER  2020
      Cine Appétit



      table of contents



















            From Editors’ Desk
      03



            3 Faces: The symbolic
      04    moves of Jafar Panahi -
                                           1 4
            Aniket Roy



            Bundesrepublik
            Deutschland (BRD)-
      07    Fassbinder's trilogy on
            post-war Germany -
            Sayor Bose



            “A Normative
            Discussion on Andrei
       10
            Rublev - Meghnad
            Mukhopadhyay
                                           1 0                                                                   0 4

            Roma and the fragility
       14   of life - Shantaneel
            Nandi











                                            0 7













                                               The Easterly


                                                    www.theeasterly.online]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Cine Appétit                                                                 ISSUE 2 | OCTOBER  2020











        E D I T O R S ’   D E S K                                                       In Picture:

                                                                                        Jafer
                                                                                        Panahi

      We,  the  creators  of  Cine  Appetite  always  look
      forward  for  coming  up  with  something  new,  yet
      immortal within the pangs of time. This issue comes
      with  three  very  important  articles  which  not  only
      tells us about film but about life in its entirety. The
      films  of  Andrei  Tarkovsky  and  specially  Andrei
      Rublev not only talks about the creation of art and
      it's  very  problems,  but  also  the  drab  sterility  in
      which  art  and  the  modern  man  gets  constantly
      tangled up and in the process art liberates itself into
      a plane of spirituality. Fassbinder's trilogy shapes the
      whole  of  Germany  in  a  go  where  the  aftermath  of
      war  is  so  vividly  portrayed  that  the  aspects  of
      civilization  gets  disjointed  and  we  face  a  world  of
      constant threats. Lastly, Jafar Panahi again raises his
      master  technique  of  equaling  the  lenses  of  camera
      and  his  vocals  against  the  restrictions  imposed  on
      art.  Panahi  focuses  deeply  on  the  varied  aspects  of
      the threats of the working class in this age and we get
      a war veteran raging against the state. Lastly, Roma
      by Alfonso Cuaron maybe marked as a path breaker
      in  world  cinema  as  it  achieves  a  great  role  in
      marking  up  the  everyday  life  of  a  common
      individual  and  Cuaron  agreeably  puts  up  an
      existentialist drama magnificently.
      This  is  a  monthly  bilingual  magazine  presented  by
      the  creators  of  The  Easterly.  The  articles  from  the
      World  Cinema  section  would  be  included  in  every
      issue  with  a  bonus    article  for  the  readers.  To  get
      your  articles  featured  send  in  your  articles  at
      submissions.theeasterly@gmail.com.
                                        Editors
                                    Cine Appétit





                           Promit Kanti Chaudhuri            Shantaneel Nandi            Bodhiswata Biswas
         Our Team:                  Aniket Roy                   Suraj  Maiti         Sankalan Bhattacharya
                                 Sabarna Ghosh                   Souvik Roy             Sourav Das Adhikary





                                                                                                         | PAGE 03]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Cine Appétit                                THE EASTERLY
         PAGE 04

                  3 FACES: THE SYMBOLIC



                MOVES OF JAFAR PANAHI







                                                           B  Y
                                                   A  N  I  K  E  T     R  O  Y































                                                                 Panahi  uses  his  camera  upon  the  folks  of  the
         Director: Jafar Panahi
                                                                 many  cultures  still  untouched  and  eventually
         Writers: Jafar Panahi, Nader Saeivar
                                                                 lost  in  the  foul  segments  of  patriarchy  and
         Stars:   Behnaz   Jafari,   Jafar   Panahi,   Marziyeh
                                                                 superstitions.  But,  this  film  becomes  much
         Rezaei, Maedeh Erteghaei, Narges Delaram
                                                                 more than that.
         Running Time: 1h 40m
         Genre: Drama
         Jafar Panahi, a filmmaker of the Iranian New            Marziyeh,  a  young  aspiring  actress  is  lost  in
         Wave  Movement  widely  known  for  his  jaw            the  very  transition  of  life  by  the  moral
         dropping depiction of the political scenario in         inequalities put forward by the foul patriarchy
         Iran  and  a  close  inhabitant  in  the  very          set  up  in  the  village.  She  remains  a  sort  of

         philosophy  of  Ritwik  Ghatak,  pushed  me             nobody or to be precise an ‘empty-headed brat’,
         further  into  the  scales  of  his  artistic  quality  but she remains true to be the most feminine
         through  his  film  ‘3  Faces’.  Panahi,  currently     and  the  most  graceful  among  the  characters
         banned  for  making  films  for  approximately          living   in   this   face   of   society.   The
         20  years,  raises  his  anti-establishment  traits     circumstances  lead  her  in  staging  a  false
         through the many voices of the people of Iran           suicide  and  filming  it  only  to  be  sent  to

         and that’s why in the process of making films           Behnaz  Jafari,  a  renowned  film  actress  and
         he  raises  a  war  against  the  State.  Gently        Jafar  Panahi.  Watching  her  act  of  suicide,
         depicted and thoroughly produced, Jafar                 Panahi and BehnazJafari are intrigued in]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[Aniket Roy                                                                             Cine Appétit


         search of Marziyeh and they take a trip to the         exitfrom the village leaving behind Marziyeh in
         village  in  Northwest  Iran.  The  film  takes  the   the house with her family. But, in the final shot
         form  of  a  road  movie,  much  more  like            Marziyeh  appears  again  running  towards
         Panahi’s    ‘Taxi’   or    Kiarostami's    ‘Ten’       Behnaz Jafari, leaving behind her family losing
         encountering  the  many  people  and  these            all  the  ties  with  the  drab  and  sterile
         whimsical  encounters  leave  traces  upon  the        functionality  of  the  Azeri  community  to  join

         viewer through the spirit of resistance.               the  two  artists.  What  struck  me  most  in  this
                                                                scene  was  that  while  these  three  people  were
                                                                leaving  the  village,  three  trucks  are  seen  to  be
                                                                approaching  loaded  with  three  bulls  for  the

                                                                upcoming     festival   and    the   viewer    is
                                                                immediately  called  upon  to  look  back  into  the
                                                                previous animal imagery symbolising the gross
                                                                breeding and the lives of people surrounding it
                                                                and  getting  less  engaged  in  matters  of  artistic

                                                                equivalence.  Immediately  the  viewer’s  minds
                                                                are flogged with the question of women liberty
         The  symbolism  is  the  driving  force  which
                                                                and the surrounding gradually sets up the view
         pushes the film into a level of poetic integrity.
                                                                that
         We’ll be looking forward to two scenes which

         in  spite  of  being  thoroughly  simple  sets  up
         ametaphor of the drabness and sterility in the
         lives of these people. The first symbolic scene
         is where an injured bull lies blocking the road.
         Panahi  has  a  conversation  with  the  owner  of

         the  bull  regarding  its  health  and  the  moral
         questions  in  its  killing.  What  is  interesting  to
         note is that the owner affirms the bull to be a
         ‘stud’  and  is  used  widely  for  breeding  and
                                                                women in these areas are objectified as nothing
         hemakes a handsome fee from it. The bull acts
         as  a  patriarchal  symbol  of  authority  and  the    but  sexual  devices  and  this  inevitable  gender
                                                                line ‘runs through this movie like a volatile fault
         driving force of breeding itself points out the
         drab overtone of sexual restraints to a plane of       line’.  Marziyeh  symbolizes  the  essence  of
         genital  gratification.  Panahi  surveys  very         rebellion and her exit from the village notably
         cleverly the grave denunciatory candour of a           points out the unwillingness of the girl being a

         world of automatic lust indulging the viewers          slave of the regressive mindset. What areleft are
         into the director’s inner world of chaos.              a  road  of  death  never  to  be  smoothened,
                                                                thoroughly    disjointed    and   an    affective

         The  second  scene  much  more  resonate  the          reminder of the current state of Iran imposing
         viewers  in  its  similarity  with  Panahi’s  ‘The     their restrictions into the many voices of artists
         Mirror’. Here, Behnaz Jafari and Jafar Panahi,         and their art.

         in the final sequence of the film are seen to



        THE EASTERLY                               ISSUE 02  |  OCT ‘20                                 |PAGE 05]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[Aniket Roy                                                                             Cine Appétit


         ‘A  humanist  in  a  theocracy,  Panahi  has  long     grandstanding’,  says  Manohla  Dargis.  Maybe
         explored  social  and  political  issues  —  poverty,  Panahi  would  agree  if  we  conclude  with  the
         women’s  rights,  authoritarianism  —  yet  without    final notion from Kurosawa’s letter to Bergman,
         the tiresome art-house wagging fingers and             ‘Let us hold out together for the sake of movies.’






















































































        THE EASTERLY                               ISSUE 02  | OCT ‘20                                  |PAGE 06]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[Cine Appétit                                THE EASTERLY
         PAGE 07
                              BUNDESREPUBLIK



                       DEUTSCHLAND (BRD)-


              FASSBINDER'S TRILOGY ON



                        POST-WAR GERMANY





                                                           B  Y

                                                  S  A  Y  O  R     B  O  S  E































         The rise of Nazism during the first half of the         seething  with  anger.  This  would  eventually
         twentieth century cumulated into the Second             pave the way for the rise of the Fuhrer, Adolf

         World  War,  one  of  the  bloodiest  wars  ever        Hitler whom many saw as the Messiah, a man
         fought   on    the   planet.   Rainer   Werner          who  would  go  on  to  make  the  Germans  the
         Fassbinder was one of the front line directors          supreme race in the world.
         of  the  German  New  Wave  Movement  which

         took  shape  during  the  60's  and  70's.  In  1980,   Many films all over the world have dealt with
         he made an epic masterpiece on television, a            this  topic  in  abundance,  thousands  of  movies
         series  running  for  almost  14  hours.  Going  by     have come out of Hollywood, Russia showing
         the  name  of  "  Berlin  Alexanderplatz",  it          the  brutal  aspects  of  this  horrific  regime
         brilliantly  explored  the  German  psyche  post        culminating  into  the  terrifying  Holocaust.
         First   World   War,    during   the   Weimar           Although most of these events are true, many

         Republic, on the back of the huge reparations           films have gone to the extent of exaggerating
         cruelly  imposed  on  them  by  the  Treaty  of         the facts and incriminating the whole German
         Versailles coupled with the great depression of         nation.  Also,  very  few  movies  have  tried  to
         1929. Germany was currently a nation                    explore the condition of Germany post 2nd]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[Sayor Bose                                                                              Cine Appétit


         World War. This is where Fassbinder steps in.          by a cruel doctor to drug addiction. Later, when
         Born  in  Germany,  he  was  quite  fascinated         she  meets  a  man  and  with  his  help,  tries  to
         with the psychology of his countrymen, both            return to stardom, she finds that the drugs have
         during pre-war and post war times. He made a           debilitated  her  nerves  and  the  fight  to
         trilogy over a period of 5 years starting from         overcome the battle with her own self seems all
         "The  Marriage  of  Maria  Braun"  in  1978,  to       the more tougher.

         "Lola"  in  1981  and  finally  "Veronika  Voss"  in
         1982. In all of these 3 films, Fassbinder casts a      Fassbinder  creates  an  atmosphere  of  tension,
         strong female character in the lead role, who          guilt, loneliness and above of all, a deep sadness
         all have become a victim of the circumstances          in  his  movies.  Peer  Raben's  intoxicating  music
         and  the  moral  bankruptcy  in  post-war              makes  the  whole  experience  all  the  more

         Germany.  In  "The  Marriage  of  Maria  Braun"        haunting  yet  beautiful.  Germany  might  have
         ,we  see  that  after  the  supposed  death  of  the   shaken  the  ugly  baggage  of  fascism  from  her
         Maria's husband, she starts living her own life        shoulders  but  the  bars  and  the  nightlife  tell  a
         which  is  eventually  interrupted  when  her          different story.
         husband  returns.  It  is  a  chronicle  of  the  rise
         and  fall  of  a  woman  during  the  World  War.      Fassbinder was not only famous as the pioneer

         Fassbinder     is   conscious     enough      in       of  New  Wave  German  Cinema,  but  also  as
         maintaining     a   non-judgmental      outlook        prominent figure of new Germany. He was the
         throughout all his films. In the case of Lola, an      beacon  of  self-righteous  anger,  mercilessly
         every  charming  lady  working  as  a  prostitute      critical  of  the  new  German  life  and  brutally

         finally falls in love with the city's new building     honest.  Fassbinder  tells  a  story  of  the  German
         commissioner,  an  upright  man  whose  value          people  after  one  of  their  worst  periods  in
         system  does  not  fit  in  with  post-war             history,  a  story  about  how  they  evolved  and
         Germany's  moral  decrepit  nature.  In  the  last     how  some  were  drawn  into  a  world  of  moral
         of  his  trilogy,  which  is  my  favourite  among     bankruptcy.     As   much    as   Fassbinder    is
         the  three,  we  come  across  the  character  of      fascinating, he is equally important.

          Veronika, a film star who has been induced

































        THE EASTERLY                               ISSUE 02  |  OCT ‘20                                 |PAGE 08]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[Get







            Published!











           I n   t h e   n e x t   i s s u e   o f     C i n e   A p p é t i t



















































                         Submit at:                                       Word Limits:


              submissions.theeasterly@gmail.com                         Articles- 400-1500 words

                                                                       Essays- 1500-3000 words







                                                                For more details:  Submission Guidelines
                                                                                  (Click here)]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[Cine Appétit                                THE EASTERLY
         PAGE 10

             A NORMATIVE DISCUSSION



                          ON ANDREI RUBLEV







                                                          B  Y
                                    M  E  G  H  N  A  D     M  U  K  H  O  P  A  D  H  Y  A  Y






























        While  watching  Rublev,  I  couldn’t  help  but        solstice,  the  end  of  spring.  The  Kliaz'ma  River
        think about Béla Tarr and his The Turin Horse.          rises north of Moscow, flows between Moscow
        Tarr developed his distinctive style over time,         and  the  Trinity-St.  Sergius  Monastery  and
        and so one should presume Rublev was a stage            eastward past Vladimir.
        in    Tarkovsky’s     development       towards

        perfecting  his  almost  magical  cinematic             Gathering firewood, Andrei gets caught up in a
        philosophy that we admire today. In this essay          village  pagan  ritual.  We  should  notice  the
        we will be discussing only some of the scenes           sounds  of  nightingales  and  of  ritual  bell
        (and  a  short  general  discussion)  of  this  three   percussion.Some  would  say  he  seeks  a  way  to
        hours long masterpiece otherwise the obvious            join his high spiritual calling and art to the real

        following rant would not have stopped.                  soil of Russian folk experience, his "civilization"
                                                                to his "culture". One way to describe the linkage
        Holiday, 1408, June                                     of  Christian  "civilization"  with  Russian  pagan
        The  scene  opens  with  the  greatest  of  all         "culture" is dual faith. Andrei is about to have a
        Russian  Icon  painters  Andrei  Rublev  and  his       "dual faith" experience himself, and so are you
        crew of apprentices and helpers on their way            if you let the film have its way.The making of a

        to  a  job  in  the  once-powerful  feudal  fortress    straw  effigy  and  the  burning  of  it  are
        city  Vladimir  in  June  of  1408.  It  is  probably   documented  features  of  peasant  ritual  on  St.
        the  evening  of  June  23,  St.  John  the  Baptist    John's Eve.
        Eve, which falls immediately after summer]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[Meghnad Mukhopadhyay                                                                    Cine Appétit


         The    sexual   license   portrayed    here   is       rival of his own brother for power in Vladimir.
         characteristic  of  peasant  spring  and  summer       A tatar Khan’s army and his one will join up at a
         rituals. Andrei stands over a smoldering camp          difficult river ford in preparation for an attack
         fire and his monkish robes catch fire. Fire and        on  Vladimir.  As  the  two  armies  link  up,  the
         water  are  central  to  the  pagan  rituals  of  St.  Khan  and  the  Russian  prince  vie  with  one
         John's Eve (they are also central to Tarkovsky's       another to see who is faster. The Russian prince

         own  personal  film  imagery).  The  men  and          recalls an event in the previous winter in which
         women  are  performing  a  characteristic  ritual      the church tried to reconcile him with his rival
         of  St.  John's  Eve.  Also  don't  miss  the  scene   brother.  The  wintry  church  is  the  great  in
         downstream from the two lines of naked folk-           Vladimir, built in 1194-1197. You can just barely
         --a white horse comes into view and begins to          make out the remarkable animal, vegetable and

         thrash  the  river's  surface  as  the  ritual  boat   human  figures  carved  in  relief  in  the  white
         approaches.                                            stone  outer  walls  of  this  ancient  cathedral.
                                                                These  figures  are  taken  to  be  themselves
         Andrei  is  captured  and  bound  in  a  stable  by    representatives  of  the  combination  of  old  pre-
         villagers  who  do  not  want  him  to  interfere      Christian   "Scythian"   motifs   with   Biblical
         with  their  dear  ritual.  Marfa  approaches  him     themes.

         and plants an earthly kiss: physical contact of
         native  paganism  with  highly  refined  and
         civilized Christianity. Notice the necklace she
         wears.  Also  notice  how  Andrei  sheds  his

         monkish  cowl  (identifying  "uniform"  of  the
         black or monkish clergy) as he decides to melt
         into  the  woods  and  rejoin  the  village  fest.  As
         the  next  morning  follows  someone  has
         squealed  on  the  village  revelers.  The  local
         landlord  and  his  ruffian  men-at-arms  on

         horseback  appear,  accompanied  by  clerical
         enforcers,  all  bent  on  doing  their  official      Two times later in this section of the film, the
         Christian  duty.  They  hope  to  run  down            Russian  prince  flashes  back  to  this  treacherous
         participants in last night's ritual. Sure enough,      "kissing of the cross" which he and his Tatar ally
         here  comes  Marfa  and  her  significant  other,      are now about to betray. The second flashback

         chased by authorities. He doesn't get away, but        occurs as the Russian prince witnesses the Tatar
         she  swims  toward  the  middle  of  the  river,       humiliation  of  the  captured  prince's  brother
         immediately  past  the  boat  carrying  Andrei,        and  family  and  receives  from  the  Tatars  the
         but  he  will  not  look  at  her.  She  splashes      vestments of the now deposed brother's power.
         bravely out to deep waters.                            The sounds of the Orthodox mass can be heard
                                                                again,  now  in  the  courtyard  as  the  Tatar  khan

         Raid, autumn, 1408                                     nervously walks his war horse back and forth in
         Now we jump ahead a few weeks to the fall of           anticipation  of  breaking  into  the  church.  A
         1408  and  the  outskirts  of  the  city  Vladimir.    dying horse comes down a stairway and falls to
         This army is led by a Russian prince who is a          the ground, bleeding to death. This is a



        THE EASTERLY                               ISSUE 02  |  OCT ‘20                                 |PAGE 11]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[Meghnad Mukhopadhyay                                                                    Cine Appétit


         disturbing  and  powerful  scene.  We  may  be        apple. The Tatar khan rides into the monastery
         more touched by this cruel death than by all          with several of his warriors. They are in a playful
         the other film portrayals of human death. As          mood.  The  khan  feeds  frozen  meat  to
         the  horse  stumbles  to  its  death,  from  the      quarrelsome  dogs.  Durochka  wants  some  too.
         church  we  hear  the  most  characteristic           What  follows  is  one  of  the  most  intriguing
         phrases  from  the  Russian  mass:  Hospodi,          "falling-in-love" scenes in all of filmdom. Andrei

         pomilui,  Hospodi,  pomilui...  [Lord,  have  mercy,  tries to intervene, but this situation is beyond his
         Lord, have mercy...].                                 or just about any imaginable power to change. As
                                                               the khan sweeps Durochka up behind his saddle
         Soon,  we  see  inside  the  cathedral  being         and  he  and  his  warriors  gallop  out  of  the
         rammed  by  the  Tatar  army.We  spy  Andrei          monastery courtyard through a roofed gateway,

         again. He is with a young blond woman. The            our time is up.
         actress is Tarkovsky's wife, and she is playing a
         paradigmatic  Russian  cultural  role:  the  holy
         fool. She is a "durochka", not able to take care
         of  herself,  but  in  her  naive  simplicity
         representing  something  very  dear  to  Russian

         tradition.  Andrei  has  made  himself  her
         protector  in  earlier  scenes,  and  now  they  are
         trapped together as the cathedral door breaks
         open.  What  a  scene,  as  the  Tatar  khan  paces

         his  horse  around  inside  the  cathedral,  asking
         the  Russian  prince  taunting  questions  about      Some  commentary  or  rather  a  casual
         the  holy  images  on  the  walls,  most  now         discussion--
         burning.  The  brave  and  defiant  Foma  is          Tarkovsky  created  a  film  about  faith  in  a  time
         tortured,  molten  lead  is  poured  into  his        when  there  were  no  films  about  religion,  apart
         mouth,  and  he  is  dragged  to  his  death  by  a   from  satire  or  anti-religion  propaganda.  At  the

         stallion  stampeded  through  the  devastated         same  time,  people  who  were  religious  have
         streets  of  Vladimir.The  traitorous  prince  is     tended  to  view  film  as  a  profane  medium,
         beset  with  deep  misgivings  about  this            inappropriate for religious topics. Andrei Rublev
         destructive adventure. Large white geese float        was  a  15th-century  monk  regarded  as  Russia’s
         from  cathedral  rooftops  to  the  disordered        greatest  icon  writer.  While  his  work  is  well

         streets  below,  all  in  slow  motion.  Andrei  and  known and celebrated throughout Russia, little is
         Durochka  are  still  in  the  church  and  try  to   known of his life except for the handful of icons
         come to terms with what has just transpired.          he  left  behind.  Tarkovsky  invented  life  for
                                                               Rublev.  It  is  then  not  an  investigation  into  the
         Tatar's Wife                                          painter’s  life,  but  Tarkovsky’s  response  to  what
         The  final  scene  I  have  selected  is  four  years  the  filmmaker  saw  and  felt  by  looking  at

         later, the winter of 1412. It is a hard winter, and   Rublev’s icons.
         famine stalks the land. Andrei is heating large
         stones and trying to transfer them to wooden          Moving  through  ‘a  sequence  of  detailed
         casks to heat water. Durochka is eating an old        fragments’ in which Rublev is sometimes



        THE EASTERLY                               ISSUE 02  |  OCT ‘20                                 |PAGE 12]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[Meghnad Mukhopadhyay                                                                    Cine Appétit


         present, sometimes only an observer, the film         the  film.Tarkovsky  plays  here  with  sound  and
         works  toward  difficult  questions:  how  is         silence,  almost  deafening  silence.  Shooting  the
         experience  related,  and  how  can  it  be           entire  movie  in  black  and  white,  Tarkovsky
         communicated?  How  can  art  be  true  to  its       finally  dazzles  the  audience  with  close-ups  of
         subject and its audience?How do you paint the         Rublev’s works, revealed for the first time during
         trinity  without  just  reducing  it  to  the  sum  of  the movie in all their brilliance and colour. After

         its parts?                                            more  than  two  hours  of  sombre  and  austere
                                                               imagery,  the  beauty  of  the  frescoes  amazes  the
         At  once  humble  and  cosmic,  Rublev  was           viewers.
         described  by  Tarkovsky  as  a  “film  of  the
         earth.”  Shot  in  widescreen  and  sharply           The  art,  born  from  the  endeavours  and

         defined  black  and  white,  the  movie  is           aspirations  of  the  artist,  is  presented  to  the
         supremely tactile—the four classical elements         audience  in  all  its  grandeur,  rising  over  the
         appearing  here  as  mist,  mud,  guttering           everyday  like  the  man  on  the  balloon  at  the
         candles, and snow. A 360-degree pan around a          beginning of the movie. This universal quality of
         primitive  stable  conveys  the  wonder  of           the  artist  and  his  work  makes  the  historical
         existence.  Such  long,  sinuous  takes  are  like    period  irrelevant,  performing  a  spiritual  sweep,

         expressionist brushstrokes; the result is a kind      casting an ethereal spell on the audience.
         of  narrative  impasto.The  film’s  brilliant,
         never-explained     prologue     shows    some        Andrei  Rublev  is  itself  more  an  icon  than  a
         medieval  Icarus  braving  an  angry  crowd  to       movie about an icon painter. (Perhaps it should

         storm  the  heavens.  Having  climbed  a  church      be seen as a “moving icon”) This is a portrait of
         tower,  he  takes  flight  in  a  primitive  hot-air  an  artist  in  which  no  one  lifts  a  brush.  The
         balloon—an  exhilarating  panorama—before             patterns are God’s, whether seen in a close-up of
         crashing to earth. Fifteenth century Russia was       spilled  paint  swirling  into  pond  water  or  the
         a  tumultuous  country,  never  really  at  peace,    clods of dirt Rublev flings against a whitewashed
         and Tarkovsky shows this in particular in the         wall.  But  no  movie  has  ever  attached  greater

         latter  half  of  the  film.  The  theme  of          significance  to  the  artist’s  role.  It  is  as  though
         conscience is present throughout                      Rublev’s presence justifies creation.































        THE EASTERLY                               ISSUE 02  |  OCT ‘20                                 |PAGE 1]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[Cine Appétit                                THE EASTERLY
         PAGE 14

             ROMA AND THE FRAGILITY



                                                OF LIFE





                                                            B  Y
                                            S  H  A  N  T  A  N  E  E  L     N  A  N  D  I






























        Roma  a  2018  film  by  Alfonso  Cuaron,  feels        between the children of her. She accompanies
        more  like  a  study  of  human  understanding          them  on  family  trips  and  they  share  strong
        than  a  film.  It  is  a  kind  of  fictional          emotions  together,  taking  care  of  the  well-
        documentary which allows us to take a look at           being of the children and of any other task that
        a  middle  upper  class  family  in  the  Roma          her  boss  entrusts  her  with.  Cleo  tries  to  live  a
        neighbourhood  of  Mexico  City  at  the                quiet life, without causing too many problems

        beginning of the 70’s. Nostalgic, profound and          for the family, assisting with whatever they ask.
        without a doubt, sometimes difficult to watch,          The parents of the children are going through a
        Cuaron’s new film is one of the most personal           separation  and  the  children  are  through  time
        films  in  recent  times.  Roma  revolves  around       without  their  dear  father.  Cuaron  does  an

        Cleo, a servant of a middle-class family living         excellent  job  of  showing  us  the  innocent  view
        in  the  Roma  neighbourhood  in  1971.  While          of the children. The reality of the situation with
        she  is  an  employee,  the  film  makes  us            the father is not so optimistic and he is actually
        understand  that  her  relationship  with  this         in a relationship with another woman and has
        family  goes  much  further  than  a  salary,  a        not  sent  a  dime  to  support  the  family.  These
        situation  which  is  still  common  in  Mexico.        are agitated times for Mexico revolving around

        Sometimes her boss scolds Cleo, either for not          protests against the Government. In one of the
        picking up the dog’s waste from the garage or           first scenes of the film, Paco mentions how he
        for  leaving  the  lights  on  at  night.  However      saw  a  soldier  killing  a  protester,  shooting  him
        there  is  a  deep  connection  between  the            in the head, an observation which seems to be a
        members of the family and Cleo, especially              normal occurrence in his life. Cuaron makes]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[Shataneel Nandi                                                                         Cine Appétit


         sure to emphasize the fragility of life from the       with  these  people.  Rarely  in  the  film  are  there
         simple  fact  of  breaking  a  window,  to  a          any  close-ups.  Instead,  Cuaron  allows  us  to
         children’s  game  to  the  events  of  the  student    savour  a  variety  of  wide-shots  with  beautiful
         movement  of  the  time  in  Mexico.  But  at  the     black  and  white  photography,  placing  Cleo  in
         centre  of  all  this  is  Cleo.  Yalitza  Aparicio    the  middle  of  some  hectic  environment,  either
         debuts excellently as Cleo. Her life takes a turn      running  down  the  street  through  pedestrians

         when  she  becomes  pregnant  with  the  cousin        and  markets,  or  in  a  house  full  of  screaming
         of her friend’s boyfriend, who isolates himself        children. It is important to recognize this way of
         from any responsibility of Cleo and her baby.          capturing  moments  since  it  allows  us  to
         Fortunately  her  employer  offers  to  provide        understand in a subconscious way how agitated
         any  help  she  needs.  We  witness  the               and noisy the world around Cleo is. The closer

         development of Cleo a person throughout the            the day of her baby’s birth, the more the world
         film.  The  camera,  however  acts  as  an             around  her  seems  to  become  problematic,
         omnipresent  power,  observing  Cleo  and  how         representing the anxiety inside her of becoming
         she  reacts  to  everything  that  surrounds  her.     a mother. Cuaron has mentioned that the film is
         Mexico  at  the  beginning  of  the  70’s  is  going   based  on  his  childhood  and  the  women  of  his
         through  a  series  of  events  that  unfold  in  the  life;  the  result  is  a  story  that  feels  strangely

         background,     which     affect   the    tense        personal,  even  for  the  viewer  whose  childhood
         environment  and  the  main  events  that  alter       may  have  been  very  different.  But  in  the  same
         the  life  of  the  family.  The  film  shows  a       way  the  fact  of  creating  a  world  and  characters
         representation    of   the    ‘Corpus    Christi       that feel so real, one leaves the film feeling that

         Massacre’,  also  known  as  El  Halconazo.  But       we  actually  know  these  people.  This  is  perhaps
         the film is actually about these people whom           one of the greatest achievements that a director
         we get to know for a short time but feel as if         can  offer  to  the  world  giving  us  characters  that
         they were our loved ones. We know the details          we  will  remember  as  is  they  have  been  part  of
         of the house and its members, the difficulty of        our  own  lives  alike  old  friends.  And  we  often
         parking  the  car  in  the  tight  garage,  how  it  is  find  our  self  asking:  what  happened  to  the

         always  filled  with  dog  waste,  the  children’s     family? Will Cleo continue to serve strawberries
         messiness and their sweet innocence, the pain          to  the  children?  Did  they  manage  to  move  on
         and  uncertainty  of  the  mother,  who  is            with  an  absent  father?  Cuaron  makes  sure  to
         struggling with an absent spouse and the need          prevent  an  ending  that,  as  in  life,  rarely  feels
         to provide for her family. Roma is a film that         completely  satisfying.  The  father  does  not

         lacks a conventional narrative drive, focusing         appear again, Cleo lost her baby, but in a certain
         more on creating and environment, recreating           way,  the  family  feels  more  united  than  ever,
         the  era  and  makes  us  feel  empathy  for  these    something that makes us happy. In this essence,
         characters.  It  is  an  experience  designed  to  be
                                                                Roma  is  a  film  about  time  and  the  fragility  of
         slowly absorbed. At the beginning of the film          life, how time can change a family, and how the
         the viewer must make the decision to be a part
                                                                circumstances  of  a  society  can  also  change
         of  it,  to  simply  observe  and  absorb  this
                                                                around  them.  The  film  begins  with  a  long  shot
         environment  and  the  problems  of  these
                                                                of the floor of the house being cleaned with soap
         characters.   By   doing    this,   it   becomes
                                                                and  water,  while  a  plane  passes  overhead,  and
         inevitable to create an emotional connection
                                                                time as well as soap water washes everything


        THE EASTERLY                               ISSUE 01 | SEPT ‘20                                  |PAGE 15]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[Shataneel Nandi                                                                         Cine Appétit


         away. In spite of how bad things can be, even          freedom  of  expression  in  Mexico  is  violated
         when  the  father  decides  to  leave  the  family,    ruthlessly  and  those  who  raise  their  voices  are
         even  though  her  beloved  Cleo  has  lost  the       killed; time just as water washes it all away. And
         baby  and  the  children  almost  drowned  and         just  like  the  planes  that  fly  over  the  turbulent
         will grow up without a father, even if the same        capital, life goes on.




















































































        THE EASTERLY                               ISSUE 01 | SEPT ‘20                                  |PAGE 16]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[Get







            Published!











           I n   t h e   n e x t   i s s u e   o f     C i n e   A p p é t i t



















































                         Submit at:                                       Word Limits:


              submissions.theeasterly@gmail.com                         Articles- 400-1500 words

                                                                       Essays- 1500-3000 words







                                                                For more details:  Submission Guidelines
                                                                                  (Click here)]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[www.theeasterly.online/]]></page><page Index="19"/></pages></Search>
